Lena Shakurova | NLP Engineer & Chatbot Developer

🛘 github.com/Shakurova 🔹 🖂 lena@shakurova.io 🔹 🚱 shakurova.io

Experienced Chatbot Developer and NLP Engineer with a background in Computational Linguistics and AI and 3+ years of professional experience applying NLP methods to real-world challenges across different domains.

Work Experience

Self-employed Chatbot Developer & NLP Engineer

Pars Labs, Netherlands

deep learning • machine learning • python • rasa • dialogflow

April 2018-present

Working on long-term projects as an NLP specialist and Chatbot Developer.

- Research on intent detection and named entity recognition approaches for an HR chatbot (Python, LUIS, padatious)
- Developed an English-speaking automated voice attendant chatbot (DialogFlow)
- Worked on the annotation project for Aspect-Based Sentiment Analysis task (Prodigy)
- Chatbot consultant for a healthcare chatbot (DialogFlow)
- Building a language learning chatbot assistant (Rasa)

NLP Architect & Chatbot Developer

COIN, Remote

′ python • DialogFlow • conversation design

August 2019–December 2019

Working in a team as an NLP Architect Chatbot expert building a financial chatbot assistant. Took part in re-architecturing the chatbot, worked on developing a strategy for expanding the chatbot to new languages and new communication platforms, improved the workflow and was guiding the chatbot development process.

NLP Research Engineer intern

TextKernel, Amsterdam

sequence labelling ● transfer learning cross-lingual embeddings ● tensorflow

November 2018-July 2019

Working full-time in a document understanding team, doing research and development on multilingual CV parsing for low-resource languages.

- Developed a universal Slavic CV parsing pipeline for 5 languages, using transfer learning and cross-lingual embeddings
- Built a cross-lingual model that performs well in zero-shot CV parsing scenario
- Developed guidelines and best practices for learning cross-lingual embeddings and doing transfer learning for our task of CV parsing
- Created new intrinsic metrics for evaluating the quality of cross-lingual word embeddings
- Improved error analysis work flow
- Presented at two conferences and published a paper

Chatbot Developer python • DialogFlow

United Wardrobe, Remote

April 2018–October 2018

Developed a prototype of a Dutch-speaking customer support chatbot.

NLP Engineer

python • machine learning • Sklearn • NER • web-crawling • databases

NCEM, Moscow

August 2016–August 2017

Core member of AI development team working full-time on building a social media monitoring system.

- Built several domain-specific text classifiers
- Developed an annotation work flow and guidelines
- Developed news content-based clusterisation system
- Improved Named Entity Recognition
- Worked on key word extraction

Junior Web Developer

TT-Consult, Remote

HTML • PHP • SEO • web crawlers

June 2014-August 2016

Editing content, debugging code, re-designing the website and doing Search Engine Optimisation.

Education

Masters of Artificial Intelligence
Radboud University

Bachelor of Computational Linguistics
National Research University Higher School of Economics

Exchange student, Computational Linguistics
University of Helsinki

Helsinki
2015–2016

Skills

o Programming Languages: Python, R

Web-development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Flask, Scrapy

o ML and NLP: SpaCy, NLTK, pandas, gensim, Sklearn, TensorFlow, WEKA

Word embeddings: Word2Vec, FastText, MUSE, VecMap

Chatbots: Rasa, DialogFlow, LUIS, padatiousData annotation: Prodigy, Toloka, Tagtog

o Databases: MySQL, SQLite, MongoDB, PostgreSQL

Other: LATEX, Jupyter Notebook, git, bash, Linux

 Sentimental Analysis, Chatbots, Word sense disambiguation (WSD), Topic modelling, Named Entity Recognition (NER), Web-crawling, Text classification and clusterisation, Duplicates detection, Sequence labelling, Information Retrieval, Automatic text summarisation

Projects

- Resume Chatbot [Link] The chatbot answers simple interview-like questions about me. Built with Python, Flask and DialogFlow.
- Web app for practising Russian Web app that automatically generates language tests for practising Russian.
 Built with Python and Flask.

Academic experience

Conferences.....

PyData Amsterdam [Video]

W languages using transfer learning"

Amsterdam
May 2019

"How to expand your NLP solution to new languages using transfer learning"

Groningen

CLIN29 Conference
"Best practices for learning domain specific cross-lingual embeddings"

January 2019

Conference ConCort on Digital Humanities

Nizhnyj Novgorod

"Instruments of Quantitative Typological Research"

October 2016

Publications.

Best practices for learning domain-specific cross-lingual embeddings, 2019 [Link]
 Shakurova L., Nyari B., Li C., Rotaru M.
 Proceedings of Repl4NLP workshop, ACL conference

Universal Dependencies for Russian: A New Syntactic Dependencies Tagset, 2016 [Link]
 Lyashevkaya O., Droganova K., Zeman D., Alexeeva M., Gavrilova T., Mustafina N. and Shakurova E.

Additional Information

Language Skills.

o Native: Russian

Advanced: English (C1 CEFR Level, CAE)

Intermediate: German, DutchBasic: Spanish, Finnish, French

| Awards |
|---|
| Orange Tulip Scholarship Russia 2017 awardee T500 2018 - list of 500 most talented young people in the Dutch digital scene |
| Extra activities. |
| o President of Language Exchange Committee, ISN Nijmegen, 2017 - 2018 |
| Interests |
| Programming · Travelling · Music · Psychology · Literature |